(858) 952-4503 New York, New York xl1005@nyu.edu

# Xinlei Lin (Daisy)

Ph.D. candidate

personal website google scholar github linkedin

I am a Ph.D. candidate in Computational Neuroscience at New York University. I study how sequences of actions in complex environments are made in AI and in humans. Currently my research projects focus on comparing deep reinforcement learning algorithms with human planning models, using large language models to predict human behavior, studying the latent factors of complex planning and improving a stochastic log likelihood estimation algorithm.

### **EDUCATION**

Ph.D. candidate in Neuroscience, New York University

2019.9 — present (Graduating 2024.10)

Research Focus: Planning and Reinforcement Learning, Computational Cognitive Science

B.S/M.S in Biochemistry, University of California, San Diego

2014.10 - 2019.3

### **SKILLS**

Tools and Languages Research Python, TensorFlow, PyTorch, Unix, Matlab, Git, R, JavaScript

Reinforcement learning and planning, Mathematical modeling, Deep learning framework, large-scale and high-dimensionality data analysis, Large language models, Human behavior modelling, Machine learning, Model fitting methodology

### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

### Learning how humans play board games with GPT Models (AAAI workshop)

2023.6 - Present

Wei Ji Ma lab + Acerbi lab

Center for Neural Science and department of Computer Science, NYU

• Trained a GPT model on a large-scale mobile game dataset (10M games) to predict different characteristics of human gameplay.

## Compare planning between AI and humans (paper, github)

2021.4 - Present

Wei Ji Ma lab

Center for Neural Science, NYU

- Trained and applied Deep Reinforcement learning models (AlphaZero type agents) in cognitive science to solve planning tasks.
- Analyzed feature representation of the trained AlphaZero networks.
- Compared the learning and planning mechanisms of AlphaZero agents with a cognitive model of human planning.

# Improve the efficiency of an unbiased log-likelihood estimation method (github)

2021.3 — present

Luigi Acerbi lab

Department of Computer Science, University of Helsinki

- Compared the efficiencies of log-likelihood estimations in different models using Inverse Binomial Sampling with different allocation methods.
- Developing a toolbox for a more efficient Inverse Binomial Sampling method that can estimate the log-likelihood unbiasedly.

# The latent factors of complex planning decisions (github)

2020.10 - Present

Wei Ji Ma lab

Center for Neural Science, NYU, NY

- Developed a battery of 8 games to run a large-scale behavioral data collection online.
- · Used dimensionality reduction techniques to investigate the individual differences and cognitive architecture of human planning

### Using neural networks to approximate Bayesian inference (paper)

2021.2 - 2021.6

• Trained artificial neural networks on a task that requires inductive reasoning and found that those networks can perform these tasks using Bayesian-like strategies without the need for an explicit computation of the log likelihood

### Large neural population analysis

2017.1 — 2019.6

Takaki Komiyama Lab

LICS

• Investigated patterns in a large neural imaging dataset to decode neural activities and the source of information segregation.

### **PUBLICATIONS AND CONFERENCES**

V. Yeom-Song, **X. Lin**, I. Kuperwajs, H. Schütt, W. Ma, L. Acerbi, **Learning how Humans Learn to Play Board Games with GPT-4IAR** (AAAI workshop 2024; FCAI AI Day 2023)

X. Lin.\*, Z.Zheng.\*, J.Topping.\*, W.Ma, Comparing Machine and human learning in a planning task of intermediate complexity (Proceedings of the Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society, 2022; The Multi-disciplinary Conference on Reinforcement Learning and Decision Making, 2022)

Gjoni E.\*, Sristi R.D.\*, Liu H.\*, Dror S., **Lin, X.,** O'Neil, K.,Arroyo O., Hong S.W., Blumenstock S., Lim B., Mishne G., and Komiyama T. **Dissection of inter-area interactions of motor circuits** (COSYNE 2023, 2022 Simons Collaboration for the Global Brain Annual Meeting, 2022 the Society for Neuroscience Annual Meeting)

### **ACTIVITIES**